Guide to the Enoch Fitch Burr Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Enoch Fitch Burr papers
1842-1888
MS 689
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
Letters to Enoch Fitch Burr of Lyme, Conn., Yale 1839, clergyman, author, and lecturer on religion and science. The Reverend Dr. Burr was a direct descendant of Nathaniel Burr of Fairfield, Conn., a brother of Jehue Burr from Aaron Burr, the vice-president, was descended. Correspondents include William Cullen Bryant, Horace Bushnell, James Dwight Dana, William Gladstone, Mark Hopkins, Henry Wadsworth Longfellow, Denison Olmsted, and Theodore Dwight Woolsey. The correspondence consists mostly of routine acknowledgements and letters of introduction.
Burr, E. F. (Enoch Fitch), 1818-1907
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
Letters to Enoch Fitch Burr of Lyme, Connecticut, from a number of prominent individuals make up these papers. Included are Henry Ward Beecher, Willian Cullen Bryant, Horace Bushnell, James Dwight Dana, William Gladstone, Mark Hopkins, Henry Wadsworth Longfellow, Samuel F. B. Morse, Denison Olmsted, Alfred Lord Tennyson, John Greenleaf Whittier, and Theodore Dwight Woolsey, among others. Unfortunately, most of the correspondence consists of letters of recommendation and acknowledgments of books received from Burr, although the letters from James Dwight Dana and a few others do contain discussions of science and religion. In addition, there are several miscellaneous items, including a partial genealogy of Burr.
Biographical / Historical
Enoch Fitch Burr studied science, then was ordained to preach in 1850; from 1850-1907 he served in a church in Hamburg, Ct.; he wrote on religion and the application of science to religion.
Religion and science; Clergy; Bryant, William Cullen, 1794-1878; Burr, E. F. (Enoch Fitch), 1818-1907; Bushnell, Horace, 1802-1876; Dana, James Dwight, 1813-1895; Day, Jeremiah, 1773-1867; Dwight, Edward S. (Edward Strong), 1820-1890; Farrar, F. W. (Frederic William), 1831-1903; Gladstone, W. E. (William Ewart), 1809-1898; Hopkins, Mark, 1802-1887; Lewis, Tayler, 1802-1877; Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth, 1807-1882; Lyman, Chester Smith, 1814-1890; Olmsted, Denison, 1791-1859; Palmer, Ray, 1808-1887; Salisbury, Edward Elbridge, 1814-1901; Seelye, Julius H. (Julius Hawley), 1824-1895; Stanley, Anthony D. (Anthony Dumond), 1810-1853; Tait, Archibald Campbell, 1811-1882; Tennyson, Alfred Tennyson, Baron, 1809-1892; Tyler, W. S. (William Seymour), 1810-1897; Vincent, John Heyl, 1832-1920; Whittier, John Greenleaf, 1807-1892; Woolsey, Theodore Dwight, 1801-1889; Burr family
- Inventory
  - Correspondence
    - Avery, P. A., 1878 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bryant, William Cullen (1794-1878) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bushnell, Horace (1802-1816), 1868 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Colvin, Clement, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Dana, James Dwight (1813-1895), 1871 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Day, Jeremiah (1773-1867), 1842 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Dwight, Edward Strong (1820-1890), 1868 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Farrar, Frederick William (1831-1903), 1888 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Gladstone, William Ewart (1809-1898), 1873 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Hopkins, Mark (1802-1887), 1871-1884 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Lewis, Taylor (1802-1877), 1871 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth (1807-1882), 1877 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Lyman, Chester Smith (1814-1890), 1871 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Olmsted, Denison (1791-1859)See also: Jeremiah Day, folder 3, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Palmer, Ray (1808-1887), 1878 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Salisbury, Edward Elbridge (1814-1901), 1876, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Seelye, Julius Hawley (1824-1895), 1875 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Stanley, Anthony Dumond (1810-1853), 1842 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Tait, Archibald Campbell, Abp. of Canterbury (1811-1882), 1873 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Tennyson, Alfred Tennyson, 1st baron (1809-1892), 1878 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Thacher, Thomas Anthony (1815-1886), 1884 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Tyler, William Seymour (1810-1897), 1876 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Vincent, John Heyl (1832-1920), 1873 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Whittier, John Greenleaf (1807-1892), 1878 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Woolsey, Theodore Dwight (1801-1889), 1860 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Yale University, Sheffield Scientific School, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letter of invitation signed by Henry Ward Beecher, Samuel F. B. Morse, and others, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous, 1872, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)